Guide to the of Harry A. Slattery Papers, 1890-1953
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harry A. Slattery papers 1890-1953
Slattery, Harry A.
60 linear feet Extent: circa 35,300
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.01203
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harry A. Slattery Papers, 1890-1953, were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library through deposit in 1953 and by gift in 1958.
Biographical Note
1887, June 13 Born, Greenville, South Carolina
1909-1912 Secretary to Gifford Pinchot, chief forester in Theodore Roosevelt's administration.
1912-1917 Executive Secretary of the National Conservation Association, appointed by its founder, Pinchot
1917-1918 Special Assistant to Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of the Interior
1919-1923 Counsel to the National Conservation Association
1923-1933 Practiced law in Washington
1925-1929 Executive and counsel for the National Boulder Dam Association
1929-1932 Counsel for the National Conservation Commission
1931-1933 Washington representative for New York Power Authority
1933-1938 Personal assistant to Harold Ickes, Secretary of the Interior Assistant to administrator of Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works
1938-1939 Undersecretary of the Interior
1939-1944 Administrator of Rural Electrification Administration (REA), from which he resigned after a conflict with the Secretary of Agriculture in 1944
1940-1942 Consultant to the power subcommittee of the advisory commission of the Council of National Defense
1944 Received LL.D. from the University of South Carolina
1949, Sept. 1 Died
Slattery attended Mount Saint Mary's College in Maryland, Georgetown University and George Washington University. As part of government efforts to indict big business for the exploitation of the country's natural resources, he was involved in Senate investigations of the Mulhall exposure during Wilson's administration and the Teapot Dome Scandal of 1921. The 1944 controversy between the REA and the Department of Agriculture over the administration of REA led to a Senate investigation. Slattery was involved in the passage of a federal coal and oil leasing measure, federal water power legislation, Alaska coal and home rule acts, and rural electrification legislation. He was a member of the National Power Policy Committee, the Energy Resources and Land Committees of the National Resources Planning Board, the Interbureau Coordinating Committee, the Federal States Relations Committee, the Society of American Foresters, the National Press Club, the Missouri Athletic Club, and Delta Theta Phi Fraternity.
Collection Overview
The Harry Slattery Papers span the period 1890-1953 with the bulk dated 1928 to 1944. They include correspondence, memoranda, writings and speeches, printed material, clippings, scrapbooks, and indexes. The collection chiefly concerns positions Slattery held during his years of public service and reflect his lifelong interest in conservation. Very few of Slattery's personal papers are included in the collection.
The bulk of the collection relates to Slattery's positions as personal assistant to Harold L. Ickes (1933-1938), as Under-secretary of the Interior (1938-1939), and as administrator of the Rural Electrification Administration (REA) (1939-1944). Other papers concern his service as secretary to Gifford Pinchot (1909-1912), as secretary of the National Conservation Association (1912-1923), as special assistant to Interior Secretary Franklin K. Lane (1917-1918), as a Washington lawyer (1923-1933), and as counsel to the National Boulder Dam Association (1925-1929). There is also information about the Teapot Dome Scandal. While information about the REA is found throughout the collection, information pertaining to the other topics is found chiefly in the Correspondence, Memoranda, Writings and Speeches, Printed Material, and Clippings Series. A typescript of Slattery's autobiography, From Roosevelt to Roosevelt, Washington, D.C., 1948, and information relating to the published work Rural America Lights Up, Washington, D.C., 1940, which is attributed to Slattery, are found in the Writings and Speeches and Scrapbooks Series. Persons studying conservation issues in the United States and the spread of electricity to rural areas would find this collection particularly helpful.
There is extensive material relating to the controversy surrounding the Rural Electrification Administration, tensions between the REA and the National Rural Electric Cooperative Association, whose executive manager was Clyde Ellis, and the conflict between Slattery and the Secretary of Agriculture Claude W. Wickard. Correspondents include Harold L. Ickes, Judson King, Basil Maxwell Manly, Gifford Pinchot, Amos R. Pinchot, John Patrick Grace, Cornelia B. Pinchot, and Philip Patterson Wells.
Subject Headings
National Conservation Association; United States. Rural Electrification Administration; United States. Department of the Interior -- Officials and employees; Boulder Dam Association; National Rural Electric Cooperative Association; Ellis, Clyde T. (Clyde Taylor); Wickard, Claude R. (Claude Raymond), 1893-1967; King, Judson; Manly, Basil Maxwell, 1886-1950; Grace, John P. (John Patrick), 1874-1940; Pinchot, Cornelia Bryce, 1881-1960; Wells, Philip Patterson, b.1868; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Lane, Franklin K.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Pinchot, Amos, 1873-1944; Lawyers -- Political activity; Lawyers -- Washington (D.C.); Rural electrification -- Law and legislation -- United States; Teapot Dome Scandal, 1921-1924; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953; United States -- Public lands
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1908-1953, undated(bulk 1928?1944).
  Chiefly typed professional letters documenting Slattery's career. About half consists of Slattery's outgoing and incoming mail. The remainder is between other individuals. Also contains a few telegrams, cards, memoranda and clippings. One folder dated Oct., 1938contains copies of microfilmed records relating to oil scandals. Arranged chronologically.
  One box of alphabetized file cards compiled by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library staff indexes letters in the Correspondence Series written to Slattery by prominent individuals. Cards record the date of the letter, place of origination, and, in some cases, the format in which it was written. This box is filed at the end of the collection.
  - 1908-1923 Apr., (19 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1923 May-1926 Aug., (20 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1926 Sept.-1928 June, (18 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1928 July-1931 Dec., (23 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1932 Jan.-1933-June, (17 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1933 July-1934 Apr. 7, (19 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1934 Apr. 8 -1935 May, (19 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1935 June-1936 July 20, (21 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1936 July 21-1937 July 10, (18 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1937 July 12-1938 May, (15 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1938 June-1939 Nov. 20, (18 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1939 Nov. 21-1940 June 20, (16 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1940 June 21-1941 Jan. 26, (15 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1941 Jan.27-1942 May 15, (16 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1942 May 16-1943 Feb. 10, (14 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1943 Feb. 11-July, (14 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1943 Aug.-1944 June, (14 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1944, July-1953, undated, (8 folders) (Box 18)
- Office Calendars, 1940-1944.
  Typed logs of daily visits and phone calls to Slattery's office, presumably while he was employed at the REA. Most are bound by year, with pages for each workday. Some entries also contain phone messages and schedules for meetings and speaking engagements.
  Arranged chronologically by volume.
  - 1940-1943, Feb., (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1943, Feb.-1944, (6 folders) (Box 19)
- Memoranda, 1908-1944, undated(bulk 1928-1940s).
  Chiefly typed material relating to Slattery's career in the form of articles, speeches, reports, and press releases. They pertain to a variety of topics including conservation, utilities, legislation, and governmental investigations. Most speeches were given by individuals other than Slattery. Also includes correspondence; printed material in the form of newsletters, invitations, conference programs, and announcements; statements; clippings; notes; lists; meeting minutes; financial records; and a few photographs. The majority of material was not originated by Slattery.
  Arranged chronologically by month, year and decade. Folders created within the chronological order for material relate to particular people and subjects.
  - 1901-1916, (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1916-1920s, Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of Interior (Box 19)
  - 1916-1920s, Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of Interior (Box 20)
  - 1917-1923, (5 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1924,Draft of Oil Brief by Harry Slattery on leases of Naval Oil Reserves (Box 20)
  - 1924-1927, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1927, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1927,Boulder Dam, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1927-1928 (Box 21)
  - 1928, (7 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1928, story of Teapot Dome Oil Scandal (Box 21)
  - 1928,Boulder Dam (Box 21)
  - 1929, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1930-1932, (16 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1933-1935, (14 folders) (Box 23)
  - 1935,Bonneville Dam Project (photographs) (Box 23)
  - 1935-1938, Kiplinger Washington Newsletter, with annotations (Box 23)
  - 1935-1938, Kiplinger Washington Newsletter (Box 24)
  - 1936-1939, (16 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1939, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1939,Addresses given at special meetings by Slattery (Box 25)
  - 1930s (Box 25)
  - 1940, (8 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1941, (3 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1941 (Box 26)
  - 1941-1944, slattery's personal files, (2 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1942, (4 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1942,REA:
    - Daily Press Digest (Box 26)
    - Directory (Box 26)
  - 1942,Winder/Pollock Investigation (Box 26)
  - 1943, (7 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1943, (3 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1943, National Rural Electric Cooperative Association – Rural Electrification Administration controversy (Box 27)
  - 1944-1953, (9 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1940s,Democratic state leaders (Box 27)
  - undated, (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - undated (Box 28)
- Writings and Speeches, 1906-1940s, undated(bulk 1920-1940s).
  Typed copies of articles, speeches, memoranda, and press releases by a number of authors; a book and book manuscript; and book orders and other miscellaneous material relating to Slattery's political career. Arranged chronologically. Slattery's two works are placed at the end of the series.
  - 1912-1940s, undated, (3 folders) (Box 28)
  - Autobiography: From Roosevelt to Roosevelt, 1906-1946(7 folders, 1 vol.) (Box 28)
  - Rural America Lights Up, 1940 and undated (Box 28)
- Miscellaneous, 1910s-1944, undated
  Photographs, notes, legal papers, reports, memoranda, clippings, receipts, copies of legislation, and lists. Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by topic. The subseries Financial Papers is placed at the end of the series.
  - 1910s-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - 1930-1931, Louis T. McFadden (Box 28)
  - 1921-1939, undated,Pictures (Box 28)
  - 1914-,Relief provisions relating to oil and gas (Box 28)
  - 1939, undated, Rural Electrification Administration (REA) (Box 28)
  - 1927-1928,Walsh bill and resolution (Box 28)
  - Financial Papers
    - 1921-1943, undated (Box 28)
- Cards and Invitations, 1930s-1945, undated
  Calling cards, greeting cards, and invitations to banquets and other public events; both personal and professional in nature. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1930s,Cards and invitations (Box 28)
  - 1930s-1945, undated, (5 folders) (Box 29)
- Printed Material, 1907-1945, undated(bulk 1920-1945).
  Primarily booklets of speeches, articles, and government reports. Also includes brochures, programs, bulletins, addresses, periodicals, articles, reports, pamphlets, and government publications. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1907-1922, (9 folders) (Box 29)
  - 1922-1924, undated,Teapot Dome (Box 30)
  - 1923-1928, (10 folders) (Box 30)
  - 1928,Hoover campaign material (Box 30)
  - 1929, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - 1930-1944, (15 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1944-1945, undated, (4 folders) (Box 32)
- Clippings, 1910-1940s, undated(bulk 1920-1940s).
  Mostly newspaper, but also some magazine clippings, from a variety of sources. Most are loose, but some are glued on paper. Includes sections of the Congressional Record relating to rural electrification. Arranged alphabetically by topic. There is a “Persons” subsection within this order in which folders are arranged alphabetically by last names of individuals.
  - Chester Lake Hunger Strike, 1944 (Box 32)
  - Conservation and Boulder Dam, 1910-1930s, undated, (6 folders) (Box 32)
  - Conservation and Reclamation, 1913-1932, (5 folders) (Box 32)
  - Conservation and Reclamation, 1933-1940s, (3 folders) (Box 33)
  - Democratic Party and Politics, 1921-1941 (Box 33)
  - Ku Klux Klan, 1929 (Box 33)
  - Nye (Gerald) Committee, 1929-1931 (Box 33)
  - Persons
    - Appleby, Paul, 1941-1944 (Box 33)
    - Brandeis, Louis, 1927-1941 (Box 33)
    - Byrnes, James, 1942-1943 (Box 33)
    - Carmody, John M., 1941 (Box 33)
    - Corcoran, Thomas, 1937-1942, undated (Box 33)
    - Davis, Chester, 1943 (Box 33)
    - Henderson, Leon, 1941-1942 (Box 33)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1915-1932, (9 folders) (Box 33)
    - Huston, Claudins Hart, 1924-1942 (Box 33)
    - Ickes, Harold LeClair, 1933-1943 (Box 33)
    - Lane, Franklin K., 1916-1920s (Box 33)
    - LaFollette family, 1924-1934 (Box 33)
    - Morgan, John Pierpont, 1927-1937 (Box 33)
    - Morrow, Dwight Whitney, 1927-1931 (Box 33)
    - Nelson, Donald, 1941-1943 (Box 33)
    - Norris, George William, 1927-1943 (Box 33)
    - Pinchot, Gifford, 1919-1925 (Box 33)
    - Pinchot, Gifford, 1926-1944, undated, (12 folders) (Box 34)
    - Reed, James Alexander, 1927-1929 (Box 34)
    - Roosevelt, F. D., 1923-1944, undated, (5 folders) (Box 35)
    - Slattery, Harry A., 1930's-1944 (Box 35)
    - Slemp, Bascom, 1923 (Box 35)
    - Smith, Alfred E., 1927-1929 (Box 35)
    - Vare, William Scott, 1926-1929, (2 folders) (Box 35)
    - Wallace, Henry, 1937-1943 (Box 35)
    - West, Ray O. and Charles West, 1928-1937 (Box 35)
    - Wickard, Claude W., 1940-1945 (Box 35)
    - Wilkie, Wendell, 1940-1941 (Box 35)
  - Price control and priorities, 1941-1943 (Box 35)
  - Public works and utilities, 1906-1928, (6 folders) (Box 35)
  - Public Works and Utilities, 1928-1944, undated, (11 folders) (Box 36)
  - Radio, 1930-1932 (Box 36)
  - Red Cross, 1931 (Box 36)
  - Rural Electrification Administration (REA), 1940-1945, undated, (6 folders) (Box 36)
  - Teapot Dome oil scandal, 1915-1921, (2 folders) (Box 36)
  - Teapot Dome oil scandal, 1922-1933, undated, (12 folders) (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous, 1915-1944, undated (Box 37)
- Scrapbooks, 1890-1944.
  Includes newspaper and magazine clippings from a variety of sources, press releases, pamphlets, correspondence and excerpts from articles chiefly relating to Slattery and issues which arose while he was administrator of the REA. Arranged chronologically. See Oversize Material section of the inventory.
  - National Rural Electric Cooperative Association, 1943-1944(2 vols.) (Box 37)
  - Rural Elecrification Administration, 1944 (Box 37)
- Indexes, 1909-1944.
  Three boxes contain indexes, presumably prepared by REA staff, referring to letters in the Correspondence Series and may also refer to material in other parts of the collection as well. These contain typed index cards filed alphabetically under the names of individuals. They include the date of correspondence, place of origination, and topic or type of material sent. Some refer to outgoing as well as incoming mail. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Rural Electrification Administration Indexes, 1939-1944(3 boxes) (Box 38)
- Oversize Materials
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1924-1944 (Box 44)
  - Memoranda
    - Memoranda, 1920-1928, undated (Box 44)
  - Writings and Speeches
    - Writings and Speeches, 1940 (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, 1928-1941 (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous: Photograph Album, 1935-1941(Photographs of people connected with the REA) (Oversize-box 43)
  - Cards and Invitations
    - Cards and Invitations, 1936-1937, undated (Box 44)
  - Printed Material
    - Printed Material, 1909-1944, undated (Box 44)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook, 1890-1939, Aug. (Oversize-box 39)
    - Scrapbook, 1939, Sept.-Dec. (Oversize-box 39)
    - Scrapbook, 1940, Jan.-Sept. (Oversize-box 40)
    - Scrapbook, 1940, Sept.-1941, Sept. (Oversize-box 40)
    - Scrapbook, 1941, Sept.-1942, July (Oversize-box 41)
    - Scrapbook, 1942, July-1943, Mar. (Oversize-box 41)
    - Scrapbook, 1943, Apr 1944, Oct. (Oversize-box 42)
    - Scrapbook, 1940-1941 (Clippings relating to Rural America Lights Up) (Oversize-box 42)